Guide to the Peter M. Riccio papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Peter M. Riccio Papers,
1911-1977
Riccio, Peter M. (Peter Michael), 1898-
11.5 linear ft. (22 boxes; 1 Flat Box; 1 Map Case).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1068
7469749
Biographical Note
Peter M. Riccio was professor of Italian and director of the Casa Italiana. Riccio was born in New York City on August 6, 1898. He graduated from Columbia College in 1921 and stayed on to teach Italian French Spanish and comparative literature. In 1929 he received his Ph. D. In 1931 he was appointed assistant professor of Italian at Barnard College, and in 1940 he returned to Columbia College to teach. He was appointed full professor and director of the Casa in 1957 and retired from both positions on July 1, 1966. His books include Perele 1936 (with S. F. Vanni); Italian Authors of Today, 1937 (with S. F. Vanni); and Ridete e Imparate 1942 (with S. F. Vanni and L. S. Trotta). Ricco died in 1990.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, memos, forms, photograph, audio cassettes, artwork, printed material, and memorabilia relating to Riccio's academic career and his direction of the Casa Italiana.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series I: Alphabetical Files
Series II: Paterno Library
Series III: Ccard File and Memorabilia
Series IV: Audio/Visual
Series V: Photographs
Series VI: Artwork
Series VII: Printed Materials
Subjects
Columbia University.--Casa italiana.; Riccio, Peter M. (Peter Michael), 1898-
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Isa and Olga Ragusa Gift, August 6, 2003 accn number.
- Series I: Alphabetical Files
  - Bigongiari Prize (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Burchell, Henry Correspondence & papers, [n.p.], 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Butler, Nicholas Murray Correspondence with Italian House Fund (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Casa Italiana Administration Board, [n.p], 1928-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University 175th Anniversary, [n.p], 1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Coro d'Italia Program and Clippings, New York, [1936?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - De Martino Correspondence re. Italian House, [v.p], 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eleonora Duse Exchange Fellowships, [n.p], 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Federation of Italian Clubs, [n.p], 1923-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fellowships - Barnard (grad.), [n.p], 1929 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Fellowships - Carducci (grad.), [n.p], 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fellowships - Crociera Atlantica (grad.), [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fellowships - Garibaldi(grad. and undergrad), [n.p], 1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fellowships - Sons of Italy, [n.p], 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fellowships - Special (Grad.), [n.p], 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dr.J.L. Gerig Various Correspondence, [n.p], 1918-1924 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dr. J.L. Gerig Miscellaneous Correspondence, [n.p], 1918-1924 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Instituto di Coltura Italiana, [n.p.], 1918-1924 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Loose Paper, Casa Correspondence, [n.p], 1918-1924 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Gerig, John L. Personal Correspondence and Appointments Pt.1, [n.p], 1911-1928 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gerig, John L. Personal Correspondence and Appointments Pt.2, [n.p], 1929-1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gerig, John L. Personal Correspondence and Appointments Pt.3, [n.p], 1933-1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - High School Teacher Awards, [n.p], 1933-1939 (Box 3A, Folder 1)
  - High School Teacher Awards, [n.p], 1933-1939 (Box 3A, Folder 2)
  - High School Student Awards, [n.p], 1929-1938 (Box 3A, Folder 3)
  - High School Student Awards (cont.), [n.p.], 1929-1938 (Box 3A, Folder 4)
  - High School Student Awards (end), [n.p.], 1929-1938 (Box 3A, Folder 5)
  - Italian Department, [n.p], 1921-1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.1, [n.p], 1924-Feb.1926 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.2, [n.p], Mar.-May 1926 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.3, [n.p], June-Oct. 1926 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.3 (cont.), [n.p], June-Oct. 1926 (Box 4A, Folder 1)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.3 (cont.), [n.p], June-Oct. 1926 (Box 4A, Folder 2)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.3 (end), [n.p], June-Oct. 1926 (Box 4A, Folder 3)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.4, [n.p], Nov.-Dec.1926 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.5, [n.p], Jan.-Feb.1927 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.6, [n.p], Mar.-Aug.1927 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.6 (cont.), [n.p], Mar.-Aug.1927 (Box 5A, Folder 1)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.6 (cont.), [n.p], Mar.-Aug.1927 (Box 5A, Folder 2)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.6 (end), [n.p], Mar.-Aug.1927 (Box 5A, Folder 3)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.7, [n.p], Sept.1927-Apr.1928 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Italian House Fund. Leases and General Correspondence Pt.8, [n.p], May-Dec.1928 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Italian House Fund. Minutes-First Meeting(with arts and certificates), [n.p], Nov.25, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Italian House Fund. Minutes-Second Meeting, [n.p], Dec.1924-Nov.1926 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Italian Society Fund. Scholarships(Grad. and Undergrad.), [n.p], 1934 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Kirby, Gustavus M. Correspondence, [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Moravia, Alberto Telegrams, Photos, Reviews (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Oldrini Bequest Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Parini, Minister Piero Correspondence, [n.p], 1929-1937 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Paterno Library Pt.1, [n.p], 1920-1935 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Paterno Library Pt.2, [n.p], 1936-1953 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Permananent Italian Book Exhibition, [n.p], 1925-1934 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Casa Fotos and Benefactors, [n.p] (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Casa Fotos (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Prezzolini,Giuseppe Personal Correspondence and Appointments, [n.p], 1925-1940 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Prezzolini,Giuseppe Poetry Course, [n.p], 1935 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Raiola, Mary E. Correspondence and Lectures, [n.p], 1934-1936 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Riccio, Peter Italian House Fund. Correspondence, [n.p], 1925-1927 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Riccio, Peter Casa Dinner Speech, [n.p], 1956 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Riccio, Peter Ms. Notes on D.Civelli (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Riccio, Peter Ms. Notes on Giovanni Gentile (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Riccio, Peter Merits Awards, [n.p], 1958 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Riccio, Peter Merits Awards, [n.p], 1959 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Riccio, Peter Awards Dinner, [n.p], 1961 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Riccio, Peter Obituaries (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Files, Family Letters, Photos, [n.p] (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Riccio, Peter Photos of Casa Italiana: A Portfolio, [n.p] (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Riccio, Peter Papers, Writings Pt.1, [n.p], 1922-1935 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Riccio, Peter Papers, Writings Pt.2, [n.p], 1936-1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence. Corrado Alvaro, [n.p] (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence. Arturo Loria, [n.p], July 9-July 17, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence. A.H. McIntyre, [n.p] (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence. A.Palazzeschi, [n.p] (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence from Giuseppe Prezzolini, [n.p] (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Riccio, Peter Xerox Copy of Complete Riccio-Prezzolini File, [n.p] (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence. A. Rosso, [n.p] (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence. C. Rossotti (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence from A. Soffici (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Riccio, Peter Personal Correspondence from E. Vallecchi (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Riccio, Peter The case of the Casa, [n.p], 1932-1941/42 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Riccio, Peter Press Clippings and Appointments-Personal Pt.1, [n.p], 1921-1944 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Riccio, Peter Press Clippings and Appointments-Personal Pt.2, [n.p], 1945-1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Riccio, Peter Press. Correspondence (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Riccio, Peter On the Threshold of Fascism (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Riccio, Peter Typescript and Notes for Article on the Department in the Faculty of Philosophy (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.1, [n.p], 1920-1926 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.2, [n.p], 1927 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.3, [n.p], 1928-1929 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.4, [n.p], 1930-1933 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.5, [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.6, [n.p], 1936-1956 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.7, [n.p], 1957 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.8, [n.p], 1958-1960 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.9, [n.p], 1961-1966 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Riccio, Peter Reports, Clippings, Fliers. Casa Italiana Pt.10, [n.p], 1967-1979 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Ryan, George J. Reception, [n.p], 1935 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Scholarships-Italiana Cham. Community (Undergrad.), [n.p], 1937-1939 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Scholarships-Pope (Undergrad.), [n.p], 1936-1938 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Sforza, Count Carlo Lecture, [n.p], 1935 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Students' Visit Correspondence and Bills Pt.1, [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Students' Visit Correspondence and Bills Pt.2, [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Students' Visit Press Clippings Pt.1, [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Students' Visit Press Clippings Pt.2, [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Students' Visit Press Clippings Pt.3, [n.p], 1934 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Students' Visit Press Clippings Pt.4, [n.p], 1934-1935 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Useful Quotes (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Series II: Paterno Library
  - "To Dr. Charles Paterno To Commemorate His Endowment Of The Charles Paterno Library And To Mark The Tenth Anniversary Of Its Founding" -- --A presentation volume of letters of congratulation and support from various presidents of universities and distinguished academics: Giuseppe Prezzolini; Nicholas Murray Butler; Mario E. Cosenza; J. Robinson; Robert F. Gannon, S.J.; Eugene A. Colligan; Tristram Walter Metcalfe; G.G. Dammann; Harry W. Chase; Americo U. N. Camera; A. Arbib-Costa; Dino Bigongiari; Gerald Groveland Walsh; Claudine Gray; Pierre Courtines; Josephine Vitillo, [v.p], 3 May 1938, (1 volume ) (Box 18)
- Series III: Ccard File and Memorabilia
  - Card file list of books and authors, [n.p], [n.d.], (ca. 500 cards) (Box 16)
  - Medal presented to the Casta Italiana by the Assessore all'Istruzione Culture e Sport della Provincia di Milano, [n.p], 7 June 1971, (4.5 cm. medal, gold plated) (Box 16)
  - Blueprint of the printed inscription on frieze of the lecture hall in the Casa Italiana, [n.p], 29 August 1927, ( Scroll) (Box 16)
- Series IV: Audio/Visual
  - Audio cassettes of various lectures, dinners, awards ceremonies, and artistic performances held at the Casa Italiana, New York, 1957-1979, (23 audio cassettes) (Box 17)
    [Includes performances by Joan Sutherland, Luciano Pavarotti, Magda Ollivero, and Sophia Loren]
- Series V: Photographs
  See also the numerous photographs in Series I.
  - Printed photographs of Albert D'Alessandro; Joseph V. Giffuni; Charles C. Rossottii; Anthony S. Gaccione; Peter M. Riccio; and the Casa Italiana, New York, [n.d.], (3 items pasted to board) (Box 18)
  - Electroplate image of Peter M. Riccio, [n.p], [n.d.], (6 x 5.1 cm. metal on woodcards) (Box 16)
  - "Blanchetto in Cnore di Gugliemo Marconi Senatore del Regno D'Italia in Occasione della Inaugurazione della Casa di Coltura Italiana Presso la Columbia University, New York", Commodore Hotel, NY, 11 October 1927, (51 x 75cm. Photograph) (Box 14/15/10)
- Series VI: Artwork
  - Original artwork by Peter M. Riccio, [v.p.], [v.d.], (ca. 300 items Mostly watercolors) (Box 387)
- Series VII: Printed Materials
  - Subseries VII.1: Casa Italiana
    - Publications, publicity files, magazines, re. the Casa Italiana, as well as Peter M. Riccio, [v.p.], 1950s -1970s, (ca. 250 items ) (Box 19)
  - Series VII.2: Books and Periodicals
    - History and the Historians in the Nineteenth Century by G.P. Gooch -- Giuseppe Prezzolini Testimone della sua Epocha -- Giuseppe Prezzolini: The American Years -- Nautical Phraseology -- Alla Maesta Christanissima di Maria de' Medici Regina di Francia e di Navarra -- Itala Gente -- Italia -- Banchetto in Onore di Guglielmo Marconi -- Architecture and Building -- The American Review of Art and Science -- Italian-American Review, [v.p.], 1911-1960s (Box 20)
    - La Basilicata nel Mondo -- The Universities of Italy -- Primo Libro D'Oro della Lingua Italiana -- Italian Treasures from Columbia University -- On the Threshold of Fascism by Peter M. Riccio, [v.p.], 1927-1977 (Box 21)